Much is said of Sao Paulo's multiculturalism
Se habla mucho de Sao Paulo, su multiculturalismo,
and of its diverse population,
las diversas poblaciones que viven aquí,
but very little is spoken of the black population.
pero poco se dice de la población negro.
Why? The historical process in in Sao Paulo has been different
¿Por qué?
from Rio de Janeiro's and Salvador's, that were capital cities.
En Sao Paulo el caso era diferente de la de Río de Janeiro y Salvador, que eran capitales.
In Sao Paulo, the black population still arrived in great numbers
En Sao Paulo la población negro entra en masa
when slavery had already started to be called into question. With the
en un momento en el que la esclavitud Ya está siendo desafiada
beginning of the coffee surge and the ending of the international slave trade,
es decir, el ciclo del café y el final de tráfico internacional,
from where did the biggest share of the black population come from?
de donde viene la mayor parte del pueblo negro de São Paulo?
It came from the so called interprovincial slave trade,
Llegó del llamado comercio interprovincial.
by which black people who were dismissed from Rio's and northeast plantations
Es decir, eran los negros que fueron despedidos de la labranza de Ríoy del noreste en crisis
and sent here to Sao Paulo.
y hacia aquí habitaron.
Every city with a big share of black population
Todas las ciudades que tenían un gran contingente de población negra
has gone through massive processes of gentrification,
Han pasado por un amplio proceso de gentrificación,
racial and social segregation.
la segregación racial, la segregación social.
It couldn't have been different with Sao Paulo.
Sao Paulo no podría ser diferente.
However, we also know
Pero, como sabemos también
that capitalism has developed in the most literal meaning of the word
Es aquí en Sao Paulo que el capitalismo se desarrollaría
here in Sao Paulo.
en las llamas formas más amplias de capitalismo.
Capitalism established new social relations of production.
Pues bien, el capitalismo viene con nuevas relaciones sociales de producción.
A new workforce is necessary to comply with that. That's the reason of
Se requiere una nueva fuerza de trabajo. De ahí que el proyecto de ley de inmigración
the immigration project, which is meant to whiten the population.
para blanquear la población.
The impact of the gentrification process on the indigenous and black populations
El proceso de gentrificación del pueblo negro y del pueblo indígena
is historical and it's still ongoing.
Es continuo e histórico
The very same process, for over 500 years.
Por más de 500 años, el mismo proceso.